Register of the Joseph Warren Stilwell papers 51001
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph Warren Stilwell papers
1889-2010
51001
Hoover Institution Archives
91 manuscript boxes, 15 oversize boxes, 1 cubic foot box, 4 album boxes, 4 boxes of slides, 7 envelopes, 3 sound cassettes, sound discs, maps and charts, memorabilia (55.2 linear feet)
Diaries, correspondence, radiograms, memoranda, reports, military orders, writings, annotated maps, clippings, printed matter, sound recordings, and photographs relating to the political development of China, the Sino-Japanese War of 1937-1945, and the China-Burma-India Theater during World War II. Includes some subsequent Stilwell family papers. World War II diaries also available on microfilm (3 reels). Transcribed copies of the diaries are available at http://www.hoover.org/library-archives/collections or at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org
Stilwell, Joseph Warren, 1883-1946
Access
Box 39 closed; microfilm use copies available. Boxes 36-38 and 40 may only be used one folder at a time.
The remainder of the collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1951, with an increment received later.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
W. B. Pettus Collection, Claremont Graduate University (Claremont, California). Pettus was president of the College of Chinese Studies in Beijing, which Stilwell attended as the army's first Chinese-language student. Pettus and Stilwell maintained a friendship through World War II, and correspondence between them is in the collection. Topics include the honorary PhD awarded to Stilwell, Chinese language instruction for the US military during World War II, and Pettus's assistance to Stilwell's daughter Alison, a painter in the Chinese style, in arranging exhibits for her across the United States.
The United States Military Academy (West Point, New York) has a collection of twenty-five items (letters, photographs, and clippings) concerning General Stilwell. These items were a gift from William R. Wigley in 1964.
William R. Gruber papers, Hoover Insititution Archives. The William Rudolph Gruber papers contain correspondence between Brigadier General William R. Gruber and General Joseph Stilwell during World War II in the China--Burma--India Theater.
John R. Shaffer papers, Hoover Institution Archives. Contains pictorial works of Stilwell.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Microfilm copies of 1941-1944 diaries (in Box 39) also available.
Transcribed copies of the diaries are available at http://www.hoover.org/library-archives/collections or at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org
Biographical Note
A chronology of Joseph Warren Stilwell's Assignments, Chronology of Promotions, and List of Decorations follows the Biographical Note.
1883 March 19 Born, Palatka, Florida
1904 June 15 B.S., U.S. Military Academy, West Point, New York
1904-1906 12th Infantry, Philippine Islands
1906-1910 Instructor, Department of Modern Languages, U.S. Military Academy
1911-1912 12th Infantry, Philippine Islands
1912-1913 12th Infantry, Presidio, Monterey, California
1913-1917 Instructor, U.S. Military Academy
1918-1919 Assistant Chief of Staff for Intelligence, IV Corps, American Expeditionary Forces
1919 Assistant Chief of Staff for Personnel, IV Corps, Army of Occupation, Cochem, Germany
1919-1923 Chinese language student, University of California, Berkeley, California, and Peking, China
1924-1925 Assistant Executive, Fort Benning, Georgia
1925-1926 Student Officer, Fort Leavenworth, Kansas
1926-1929 Battalion Commander, 15th Infantry, Tientsin, China
1929-1933 Instructor, Infantry School, Fort Benning, Georgia
1933-1935 Reserve duty, San Diego, California
1935-1939 Military Attaché, U.S. Embassy, Peking, China
1939-1940 Commander, 3rd Infantry Brigade, Fort Sam Houston, Texas
1940 Promoted to Major General
1940-1941 Commander, 7th Division, Ford Ord, California
1941-1942 Commander, 3rd Army Corps, Presidio of Monterey, California
1942 Promoted to Lieutenant General
1942-1944 Commanding General, U.S. Forces in China-Burma-India Theater
1944 Promoted to General
1945 Commander, U.S. Ground Forces Commander, 10th Army, Pacific Theater
1945-1946 U.S. War Equipment Board, Washington, D.C.
1946 Commander, 6th Army, Western Defense Command, Presidio of San Francisco, California
1946 June 25–July 31 Observer, Bikini Atomic Bomb Tests
1946 October 12 Died, Presidio of San Francisco, California
Chronology of Joseph Warren Stilwell's Assignments
Prepared by John Easterbrook.
1904 June 15 Graduated from United States Military Academy, West Point, New York
1904 June 16 - September 14 Graduation leave and travel to West Coast
1904 September 15 - November 7 En route to Camp Jossman, Guimaras, Philippine Islands ( USAT Sheridan, October 1-29, 1904)
1904 November 7 - 1906 April Camp Jossman, Guimaras, Philippine Islands (in the field, Samar, Philippine Islands, February 3, 1905), 12th Infantry
1906 April 9 - August 21 Graduated from United States Military Academy, West Point, New York
1906 August 22 - 1910 December 18 Department of Modern Languages, United States Military Academy (intelligence gathering trip through Guatemala, June 20-August 9, 1907; trip through Mexico, June 28-August 1, 1908; trip to Honduras, Salvador, and Guatemala, June 25-August 4, 1909)
1910 December 19 - 1911 January 31 Travel to West Coast and en route to Philippine Islands ( USAT Sherman, January 5-31, 1911)
1911 February 1 - 1912 February 11 Fort William McKinley, Philippine Islands (Company D, 12th Infantry, June 4, 1911; leave in Japan and China, September 15-December 14, 1911); returned to the U.S. with Company D, 12th Infantry
1912 February 11 - 1913 April 29 Presidio of Monterey, California, Company D, 12th Infantry
1913 April 30 - May 31 Leave
1913 June 1 - 27 Fort Niagara, New York, for tryout for Army Infantry Rifle Team
1913 June 28 - August 17 Leave and travel
1913 August 18 - 1914 June 2 Department of English and History, United States Military Academy
1914 June 3 - 14 Travel to Madrid, Spain ( Lorraine, June 3-10, 1914)
1914 June 15 - August 6 Madrid, Spain, for Spanish language course
1914 August 8 - 27 Travel to the U.S. ( RMS Ivernia from Gibraltar to Boston, August 8-20, 1914) and leave
1914 August 28 - 1915 April 21 Department of Modern Languages, United States Military Academy
1915 April 22 - 26 Travel to Madison Barracks, New York
1915 April 27 - September 27 Madison Barracks, New York, for "duty with troops" (Companies H, L, and K, 3rd Infantry)
1915 September 28 - 30 Leave
1915 October 1 - 1916 June 25 Department of Modern Languages, United States Military Academy
1916 June 12 - August 12 Camp of Instruction, Regular Troops, Plattsburg, New York (Company M, 1st Battalion, Station Training Regiment/8th Training Regiment
1916 August 12 - 1917 August 24 Department of Modern Languages, United States Military Academy (with additional duty in the Department of Tactics starting in June 1917)
1917 August 25 - December 18 Camp Lee, Virginia, 80th Division (Brigade Adjutant, Camp Quartermaster, Commandant Quartermaster Training School, Commandant School of Arms and Assistant Chief of Staff, G-2)
1917 December 30 - 1918 January 19 En route to France ( USMS New York from New York, January 7, 1918, arrived in Le Havre, France, January 19, 1918)
1918 January 19 - February 6 General Headquarters, American Expeditionary Forces, Chaumont, France
1918 February 6-10 Travel to British 30th Division and on to British 58th Division
1918 February 10-15 With British 58th Division, La Fère Sector
1918 February 16-28 Army Schools, Intelligence Course, Langres, France
1918 February 28 - March 17 General Headquarters, American Expeditionary Forces, Chaumont, France
1918 March 20 - April 29 With French 17th Corps, Verdun Sector
1918 April 30 - June 5 General Headquarters, American Expeditionary Forces, Chaumont, France
1918 June 6-15 With U.S. 2nd Corps, G-2 Section
1918 June 19 - 1919 January 20 Assistant Chief of Staff, G-2, U.S. 4th Corps (Toul Sector, in Battle of St. Mihiel; temporary duty, 1st Corps, August 8-10, 1918)
1919 January 20 - June 23 Assistant Chief of Staff G-1, 4th Corps, Army of Occupation, Cochem, Germany
1919 July 5-15 En route to the U.S. ( Lorraine)
1919 July 16 - August 29 Leave (one month) and travel to California
1919 August 29 - 1920 May 17 Chinese language student, University of California, Berkeley, California
1920 May 18 - August 4 Leave
1920 August 5 - September 20 En route to China ( USAT Madawaska to Manila, August 5-31, 1920)
1920 September 20 - 1923 July 8 Chinese language student, Peking, China
1923 July 8-31 En route to the U.S. ( USAT Thomas)
1923 August 1 - September 9 Leave and travel to Fort Benning, Georgia
1923 September 10 - 1924 May 29 Student, Advanced Officers' Course, Infantry School, Fort Benning, Georgia
1924 May 30 - 1925 May 30 Assistant Executive, Fort Benning, Georgia
1925 May 31 - August 21 Leave and travel to Fort Leavenworth, Kansas
1925 August 22 - 1926 June 30 Student Officer, Fort Leavenworth, Kansas
1926 July 1 - September 28 Leave and travel to Tientsin, China (sailed on USAT Thomas, August 20-September 28, 1926)
1926 September 29 - 1928 February 22 15th Infantry, Tientsin, China
1926 October 1 - December 15 Commander, Provisional Battalion, 15th Infantry
1926 December 6 - 1927 April 30 Commander 2nd Battalion, 15th Infantry
1927 May 1 - October 31 Regimental Executive Officer, 15th Infantry
1927 November 1 - December 23 Commander, Provisional Battalion, 15th Infantry
1927 December 24 - 1928 February 22 Regimental Executive Officer, 15th Infantry (trip to Korea and Japan, September 5-25, 1927; trip to Japan, September 22-October 30, 1928)
1928 February 22 - June 30 Post Executive Officer, Tientsin, China
1928 July 1 - 1929 April 16 Chief of Staff, United States American Forces in China (detached service for one month effective March 10, 1929; trip to Korea and Japan, March 10-April 1, 1929)
1929 April 17 - May 31 En route to the U.S. ( USAT Grant, April 17-May 7, 1929, to San Francisco and then New York via Panama, May 14-31, 1929)
1929 June 1 - July 9 Leave and travel to Fort Benning, Georgia
1929 July 10 - 1930 May Instructor in Tactics, Fort Benning, Georgia
1930 May - 1933 May 30 Chief of First Section (Tactics) and Instructor, Fort Benning, Georgia
1933 June 6 - 1935 May 19 Reserve duty in San Diego, California
1935 April 20 - June 4 Leave and travel to San Francisco, California
1935 June 5 - July 6 En route to China ( USAT Grant)
1935 July 7 - 1939 May 13 Military Attaché to China and Siam, Peking, China (26 field trips within China and Siam)
1939 May 13 - August 14 Leave (Indo-China, Siam, Malay, Java, and Philippines) and en route to the U.S. ( USAT Grant, July 24-August 14, 1939)
1939 August 16 - September 23 Leave and travel to Fort Sam Houston, Texas
1939 September 24 - October 8 Commander, 3rd Brigade, Fort Sam Houston, Texas
1939 October 8 - 1940 June 28 Infantry Commander, 2nd Division, Fort Sam Houston, Texas
1940 July 1 - 1941 July 25 Commanding General, 7th Division, Fort Ord, California
1941 July 25 - December 23 Commanding General, 3rd Corps, Presidio of Monterey, California
1941 December 24 - 1942 January 23 Washington, D.C. (planning North African invasion)
1942 January 23 - March 4 Planning, assembling staff, and en route to China
1942 March 4 - 1944 October 26 Chief of Staff to the Supreme Commander of the China Theater; Commanding General of U.S. army forces in the China Theater of Operation, Burma, and India (o/a June 22, 1942, evolved to Commanding General, China-Burma-India Theater); and subsequently Deputy Commander, Southeast Asia Command
1944 October 26 - 1945 January 22 En route to the U.S., leave, and waiting for new assignment per verbal instructions from General George C. Marshall, Army Chief of Staff
1945 January 24 - June 21 Commanding General, Army Ground Forces
1945 June 23 - October 15 Commanding General, Tenth Army, Okinawa, Japan
1945 November 1 - 1946 January 19 War Equipment Board, Washington, D.C.
1946 January 22 - February 28 Commanding General, Western Defense Command, Presidio of San Francisco, California
1946 March 1 - October 12 Commanding General, Sixth Army, Presidio of San Francisco, California (observer, Bikini Atomic Bomb tests, June 25-July 31, 1946)
1946 October 12 Died at Presidio of San Francisco, California, at age 63
Sources: Diaries, orders, papers, and notes in the Joseph W. Stilwell papers, Hoover Institution Archives, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, Stanford University, Stanford, California, and personal letters in the possession of John Easterbrook. Compiled by John Easterbrook, April 2002.
NOTE: Some time intervals shown between assignments are assumed to be a small number of leave days and/or travel time, and in some cases clearing customs following international travel. Major blocks of leave time are noted. Single day differences were occasionally noted between Stilwell's diaries, summary notes, and orders. In these cases preference was given to daily diary entries when available.
Chronology of Promotions
Prepared by John Easterbrook
1904 June 15 Second Lieutenant
1911 March 3 First Lieutenant
1916 July 1 Captain
1917 August 5 Major, AUS (accepted August 21, 1917)
1918 August 26 Lieutenant Colonel, AUS (accepted September 11, 1918)
1919 May 6 Colonel, AUS (accepted May 10, 1919)
1919 September 14 Returned to grade of Captain
1920 July 1 Major
1928 May 6 Lieutenant Colonel
1935 August 1 Colonel
1939 July 1 Brigadier General (accepted August 5, 1939)
1940 October 1 Major General, AUS (aaccepted October 2, 1940)
1942 February 25 Lieutenant General, AUS
1943 September 1 Major General, Regular Army
1944 August 1 General
List of Decorations of Joseph Warren Stilwell
Prepared by John Easterbrook
United States. Army decorations
Combat Infantryman's Badge
Distinguished Service Cross
Distinguished Service Medal with Oak Leaf Cluster
Legion of Merit, Degree of Chief Commander
Bronze Star (posthumously)
Air Medal (posthumously)
Philippine Campaign Medal
World War I Victory Medal with clasps for St. Mihiel and Defensive Sector
American Defense Service Medal
American Campaign Medal
Army of Occupation of Germany Medal
Asiatic-Pacific Campaign Medal with one silver star in lieu of five bronze stars
World War II Victory Medal
Foreign decorations
Légion d'Honneur, Chevalier, France
La Solidaridad, Panama
Order of Leopold with Palm, Degree of Grand Officer, Belgian (posthumously)
Croix de Guerre with Palm, Belgian (posthumously)
Mentioned in Despatch for Distinguished Service, British
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Joseph W. Stilwell in the Hoover Institution Archives constitute an extremely valuable resource for scholars and researchers interested in military history in general and in the history of World War II in the China-Burma-India Theater in particular. The historian Barbara W. Tuchman, an authority on the subject of Joseph W. Stilwell's life and career, used these primary source materials extensively for her book, Stilwell and the American Experience in China, 1911-45. These materials contain not only military information, such as plans of troop deployment, determination of war strategy, and handling of supplies, but they also bring to life General Stilwell's personality and character. He was proficient in many languages, traveled widely in connection with his tour of duty, and the papers reflect his interest in and admiration for different cultures.
Handwritten Original Diaries with illustrations constitute the most interesting and significant segment of the collection. Therein Joseph W. Stilwell recorded details of his daily life, his thoughts on various subjects, his trips, his personal life, and important information received from radio messages or via telephone calls. His thoughts, as reflected in these diaries, often developed into plans of military action. General Stilwell never intended that his diaries would be seen by anyone else and he frequently used them to vent the frustrations he faced. The language is often blunt, and while they may not reflect his daily behavior, they do provide insights to his character and strengths. Transcripts of Diaries are also available.
The American Expeditionary Forces, IV Army Corps File contains information relating to the time Joseph W. Stilwell spent at the Army General School in Langres, France, for training, his service with the French army at Verdun, and his work as the Corps' Chief Intelligence Officer. The China-Burma-India Command File provides significant documentation on the situation in the Pacific and in the China-Burma-India sector, Stilwell's performance as a commander, his grasp of strategic issues, and his persistence in upholding the course of action he believed to be viable. This series also traces the history of his disagreements with Chiang Kai-shek, which led to his recall.
The Career File and the Personal and Family File taken together paint a picture of Joseph W. Stilwell as a man totally dedicated to his family and his country. Various school and family records provide an interesting insight into his family affairs and his performance at school. The Literary File reflects his writing skills, as shown by the articles, essays, musical lyrics, poems, and speeches therein.
The Memorabilia series, consisting of Joseph W. Stilwell's personal effects, gifts, and souvenirs from the army, provides a rare and interesting opportunity to learn about life in the army with all its paraphernalia. The Oversize Materials include cartoons, various documents and drafts, maps (including some annotated by Stilwell), and posters, and form an important segment of the collection.
The Scrapbooks, a collection of clippings, messages, photographs, and souvenirs, contain a wealth of information relating to Stilwell's life. The Lantern Slides, depicting scenes of life and people in China, are exquisite and unique features of this collection. And among the Sound Recordings, the recorded messages from Burma and a speech given in San Francisco, California, reveal Stilwell's skills as a speaker and his sense of humor.
The Incremental Materials, while complementing the original collection acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1951 from Mrs. Joseph W. Stilwell, include some new information about Joseph W. Stilwell's personal life and his career in the army. His writings in general, and his letters to his wife in particular, are a significant component of the incremental materials. The issuance of the Stilwell postal stamp, as well as the process leading to this event, represents the nation's tribute to a remarkable man and general.
Finally the Photographs, including a number of postcards, depict beautiful scenes and people from China, Japan, the Philippines, and many cities of the United States. They also reveal a very personal side of Stilwell at his residence in Carmel, California, and in his army life as a West Point cadet, as a soldier during his early assignments in Europe, and as a commander of the China-Burma-India sector, in the Philippines, and in the Pacific.
This register is an expanded and more detailed version of an earlier version created after the collection was received. Folder numbers and documents not previously mentioned have been added, but the order of the series has been retained, with one exception –- the American Expeditionary Forces series now appears at the beginning. However, new series have been added, the largest one consisting of the incremental material received since the completion of the initial register and listed at the end of the register. Separate series have also been created for the recently created diary transcripts, as well as for the scrapbooks, memorabilia, oversize materials, glass slides, photographs, and sound recordings (sound cassettes), which previously were to be found in the miscellany series.
Audiotapes.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945.; Slides (Photography).; Sound recordings.; Stilwell Road.; United States. Army--Officers.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Burma.; World War, 1939-1945--China.
- American Expeditionary Forces, IV Army Corps File, 1912-1939
  Scope and Contents note
  Announcements, army manuals, bulletins, charts, clippings and other printed matter, communiqués, correspondence, intelligence data, lectures, lists, maps, memoranda, notes, operation plans, orders, reports, summaries of foreign press, tables, telephone messages, and miscellany relating to Joseph W. Stilwell's training at the Army General Staff College at Langres, France, his service in the French army at Verdun, and his work as Chief Intelligence Officer, IV Army Corps, American Expeditionary Forces, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Includes material related to the French and German armies. Some brittle pamphlets have been removed from box 1. Cover sheets of these pamphlets and information regarding their availability, either in the Hoover Library, in the Stanford Libraries, or elsewhere, can be found in the first folder.
  - Army manuals, 1912-1919 (Box-folder 1: 1-10)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes maps and reports.
  - Bulletins, 1918-1919
    - Bulletin, Intelligence Section, IV Corps, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 1-5)
      Includes numbers 1-55.
    - Bulletin de renseignements, French VIII army, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 1-4, Box-folder 2: 6-13)
      Includes numbers 175-266, 268-276, 278-284, 286-302, 304, and 308-315.
  - Captured German documents, 1914-1918
    - Announcements, fliers, and posters, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Certificates, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Currency notes, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Hand bills, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Military documents, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 9)
      Includes letters, maps, messages, plans of operations, and proclamations.
    - Miscellany, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Clippings and printed matter, 1914-1939
    - Undated (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - 1914-1917 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - 1918-1939 (Box-folder 3: 13-16)
  - Field orders and notes, 1918-1919
    - Instructions and plan of operations, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 3: 17)
      Includes communication, supplies, and evacuation.
    - Notes, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - General orders, 1918-1919
    - III Corps, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - IV Corps, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 3-5)
  - Histories, 1918-1923
    - German army, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 4: 6)
      Histories of Two Hundred and Fifty-One Divisions of the German Army which Participated in the War (1914-1918). Compiled from records of Intelligence Section of the General Staff, American Expeditionary Forces, at General Headquarters: Chaumont, France.
    - U.S. Army. IV Corps, 1918-1923
      - Lists, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 4: 7)
      - Memoranda, 1918-1923 (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - Notes, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - Reports on the activities of the Intelligence Section, 1st Division and 42nd Division, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Insignia chart for French army, undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Intelligence data, French VI Corps, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    Includes maps and related materials.
  - Intelligence reports, 1917
    - French army, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 1-5)
      Includes bulletins, communiqué, letter of authorization and list of addresses, maps, and report.
    - U.S. Army. IV Corps, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 5: 6-18)